<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at Whitehall, Sunday, January 25, 1684/5 being the feast of St. Paul's conversion / by Henry Dove ...</title>
            <author>Dove, Henry, 1640-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36455</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11805537</idno>
  <idno type="VID">49433</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240866748</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8563</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11805537</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36455)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49433)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 529:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at Whitehall, Sunday, January 25, 1684/5 being the feast of St. Paul's conversion / by Henry Dove ...</title>
                  <author>Dove, Henry, 1640-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benjamin Tooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XVI, 4-5 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Fasts and feasts --  Church of England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49433:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49433:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING AT WHITEHALL, SUNDAY <hi>January</hi> 25. 1684/5.</p>
            <p>Being the FEAST of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Conversion.</p>
            <p>By HENRY DOVE, D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majesty.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Published by the Special Command of His Late Majesty of Ever Blessed Memory.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:49433:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49433:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Acts 16. 4, 5.</bibl>
                  <p>And as they went through the Cities, they delivered them the Decrees for to keep, that were ordained of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles and Elders which were at Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem. And so were the Churches established in the Faith, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in number daily.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AMong the sundry Arguments which confirm the truth of the Gospel, the success it found in the world, and the wonderful effects it produced in the hearts and lives of the new Converts, has been always rightly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49433:3"/> judged an evident demonstration of its Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity and Power: And indeed, had we no other evidence of its truth and efficacy, but what the instance of St. <hi>Paul</hi> affords us (for whose miraculous Conversion we this day glorifie God) his zeal, and courage, and constancy in the Faith, the continual la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and sufferings of his life, from the time he was stopt in his Journey, to the last moment of it, were enough to prove it. For if we consider what a strange alteration was all of a sudden wrought in him, how the stream of his words and actions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs, were turned quite into another chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, and how he preached the Gospel with all boldness, which once he endeavoured to destroy with the greatest fury, we must needs conclude the efficacy of that Truth which wrought such a change in him. A little before, we read how he assisted at the shed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the innocent bloud of St. <hi>Stephen</hi> the first Martyr, and shewed his consent to his death by holding the garments of them that slew him; next what havock he made of the Church at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> entring into every house, and haling men and women to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49433:3"/> prison, being implacably mad against all that called on the Name of Christ: And soon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, we find him posting to <hi>Damascus</hi> with Letters from the High Priest, breathing forth nothing but threatnings and slaughter against the Disciples of our Lord. But now of a ravening Wolf that devoured the sheep of Christ, he becomes a follower of the Lamb and a Pastour of his flock; the furious Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risee is turned into a zealous but meek A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle, and instead of menacing death to the Christians, none more ready than he to suffer the loss of all things, and to lay down his life for the sake of Christ and them. And what could induce him to forego his Acquaintance, Kindred, and Friends, his Reputation and Interest in the World, his enjoyments and hopes, and all the outward comforts of humane life toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and instead of these, to meet with nothing in exchange but troubles and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, persecutions and poverty, bonds and afflictions, and death it self, and to suffer all these with joy and gladness, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and light of his Conscience, through the mighty influence of that heavenly voice,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49433:4"/> which smote him down to the ground, and entred even into his Soul, and the inconte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable evidence of this great Gospel-Truth, which is indeed the foundation of all the rest he preached, That that very Jesus whom he had persecuted was Christ the Lord?</p>
            <p>But that which is most for our present pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, is, his unwearied diligence and zeal in the discharge of his Office, and spreading the Gospel throughout the world; by which it is manifest how resolved he was to testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his Repentance among all Nations, and to make what amends he could for his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer injuries and misdoings: And here should we follow him in his travels, we might sooner be tired than relate with what wing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed speed he compassed sea and land to root out the Idolatry of the Nations, and to fetch in both Jews and Gentiles to the fold of Christ: what pains he took for almost forty years in planting and watering, in setling and governing the Church of God; how he laboured more abundantly in Word and Doctrine, in Journeys and Visits, in Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Writing than all his Brethren; for while the other Apostles spent the chief of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49433:4"/> their time and care in some particular Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, his Province was as large as the known world: Though their power was equal, yet the pains of St. <hi>Paul</hi> were multiplied, in that he had <hi>the care of all the Churches,</hi> eonfirming the faithful, and confuting the erroneous by the soundness and power of his Doctrine where-ever he came, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing such rules of Discipline and Order, as were sufficient to compose the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which might or did arise, and to keep all Christians in peace and unity to the worlds end.</p>
            <p>An eminent instance of which, was his care in the first place of the Church at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> which was greatly divided about Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcision and the Mosaic Rites, till St. <hi>Paul</hi> had setled it by procuring the decrees men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Text, and causing 'em to be kept throughout the Churches. And it is highly probable he was more than ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inclined to begin with <hi>Antioch,</hi> that he might stop the progress of such growing errours betimes, and leave an example to after-ages how the Church should cure or prevent Schisms.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49433:5"/>
            <p>For the right understanding of which, and clearing the way to the words before us, give me leave a little to state the case and open the question that was now in hand: When the Religion of Christ began to gain ground in the world, as it was first preached at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> so the Jews were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally the first Converts; But when they perceived that God had opened the door of Faith to the Gentiles also, the Spirit which lusteth to Envy began to work afresh among 'em, and though they had given up their names to Christ, yet they retained a relish of the old Leaven, being wonderfully in love with the Rites of <hi>Moses</hi> still: and hence the Jews at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and some of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sees at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> who kept no doubt their old correspondence, declared with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, That <hi>except the Gentiles were circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised</hi> as well as themselves, <hi>they could not be saved:</hi> But St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who knew their temper well by his own experience, ever since he was one of the same Sect, opposed 'em vehemently, disputing and reasoning the case with 'em; And when he saw they were deaf to Arguments, and resolved to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49433:5"/> hold the conclusion still, he proposes such an expedient, as no man in reason can or ought to refuse, that they would stand to the decision of their Superiours and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in the Church. To this they all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented, as the most reasonable thing imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; and therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas, and certain other of them</hi> are hastned away to <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> to consult <hi>the Apostles and Elders</hi> there <hi>about this question;</hi> they forthwith assembled to consider of it, and having heard and debated the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they gave their Sentence, and made their Decrees, and wrote their Letters to this effect: <q>That the Jewish Converts were disturbers of their Brethren without any cause or warrant, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> had done what they ought in opposing their strange Doctrine; That <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were sent to them on purpose to tell 'em at large by word of mouth, what was briefly contained in their Synodical Epistle; and in short, that the Gentiles should no more be molested about Circumcision, but that it should suffice for the present, if they observed what they professed already, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49433:6"/> the Precepts of the Sons of <hi>Noah.</hi>
               </q> These Decrees being made, were immediately dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers'd among all the Churches depending on <hi>Antioch</hi> or <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and particularly here by St. <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Silas</hi> through <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Cilicia,</hi> at <hi>Derbe</hi> and <hi>Lystra</hi> Cities of <hi>Lycaonia;</hi> And as they went through the Cities, &amp; either visited the Churches they had already planted, or gathered new ones, <hi>They delivered them the Decrees for to keep, that were ordained of the Apostles and Elders which were at Jerusalem: And so were the Churches established in the Faith, and increased in number daily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ignorant, that the words thus open'd and explain'd, with relation to the context, would afford variety of Discourse, of Councils and Synods, of Mother-Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and their dependencies, of Bishops and Pastours, and the Power committed to them by Christ (the great Bishop of our Souls) in things pertaining to God and his Church; of the duty of Inferiours, whether Clergy or Laity, in a meek submission to their just Authority and Discipline; of calling Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, managing Debates, and deciding Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies, and the like: But seeing these
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49433:6"/> are Subjects much fitter for the Schools, or a-Convocation, than for the Pulpit, I shall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 'em no further than as they fall in with the Text, wherein we may observe these three Propositions, that express the main im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Decrees may be made for the well ordering and governing the Church of Christ. <hi>They delivered the Decrees which were ordained of the Apostles,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Decrees well made and promulgated ought to be kept; <hi>They delivered them the Decrees,</hi> which were sufficiently made known by being delivered, and they deliver'd 'em to this end, <hi>That they might be kept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Decrees well made and well kept, conduce very much to the establishment and increase of the Church. <hi>And so were the Churches established in the Faith, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in number daily.</hi> Of these I shall briefly speak in their order, and then apply the whole with a word I hope in season.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49433:7"/>[1.] Decrees may be made for the well ordering and governing the Church of Christ: 'Tis evident that the Apostles and Elders here enacted such, and who doubts but they did what they ought to have done, and that they had power so to do? And if in those early days, when there were so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny eminent persons qualified with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gifts and endowments, each one of which had both Wisdom and Authority sufficient to determine what was needful; If then it was judged the best expedient for composing differences in the Church, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the definitive sentence of the Church representative, and the sentence of their Governours, did finally conclude and quiet the Litigants, then doubtless 'tis a leading case for all succeeding Governours in the Church, when they are lawfully summoned and met together to do the like, and does not onely warrant their power in making such Decisions and Decrees, but is likewise the pattern of our ready compliance and submission to their just Injunctions: What was then deem'd necessary for the present
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49433:7"/> exigence of affairs, may without all questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, upon an occasion of the like nature, be done again? And though the extraordinary gifts of those Primitive times be ceased, the work being long since done for which they were given, yet that the ordinary power of the Apostles and Elders continues still in their Successors, is plain from hence; because the work for which that power was given is still in doing, and will not be finished till the end of all things: For while Christ was yet upon Earth he appointed the Apostles, and the Seventy; when he was risen again from the dead, he confirmed and enlarged their Power; and when he was ascended up on high (says St. <hi>Paul) he gave some A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, and some Prophets, and some Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists, and some Pastors and Teachers,</hi> [Eph. 4. 11.] Some extraordinary for those ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ages, whose Calling and Office ceased when the Church was once increased; but lest we should think that the care of Christ was withdrawn from after Ages, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle adds the Ordinary also, whose Errand it is to perform continually whatever is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary <hi>For the perfecting of the Saints, for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49433:8"/> the work of the Ministry, for the edifying of the Body of Christ</hi> [v. 12.] And further still, lest any man should think (as some of late have daringly affirmed) that their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling also was onely Temporary, to last for a little time, till all should be taught of God, and so become their own Pastors, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle seems to foresee, and provides against such Tenets, by securing the stability of their power till the end of all things; for so he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes [<hi>v. 13.] Till-we all come in the unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the measure of the stature of the fulness of Christ.</hi> As long as this world lasts, and men remain dwelling upon Earth, so long will Christ have a Church Militant here below; and as long as his Church is Militant here, so long will he maintain such a Succession and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Order of men, such Overseers of his Flock, such Pastors and Teachers of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as may govern and guide 'em in the ways of truth and peace, and so conduct 'em to his everlasting Kingdom. For so he assured his Apostles, when he sent 'em forth to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Disciples of all Nations; <hi>Go</hi> (faith he)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49433:8"/>
               <hi>and remember that all power is given unto me in Heaven and in Earth;</hi> by that power I now send ye, by the same power I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and assist you and your Successors; for, <hi>lo I am with you alway, even unto the end of the world,</hi> [St. Matth. 28.] Not with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles in person; for they all finished their course not long after, therefore with their Successors: The same power which enabled them to perform their Apostolical Function while they lived, fitted them also for the ordaining of others, and the committing of a standing power to a successive Ministry, even unto the end of the world. How far this power extends, and in what it is chiefly to be exercised, is besides my purpose to enquire here; I shall only consider it in the least and lowest degree, as it relates to things indifferent, and is used in making De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees for the maintaining of order and peace among us; for these (it seems) were some of the things which disturbed the Church of <hi>Antioch;</hi> and these are the things which through the perverse Disputings of some that oppose themselves, and deceive the Hearts of the simple, have sadly divided
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49433:9"/> the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Now we need (I conceive) no more than this, to convince the minds of such as seek and ensue Peace, [<hi>That the Church hath power</hi> particularly <hi>to decree Rites and Ceremonies</hi>] as our Articles express it; that either we must find every thing which respects the Worship of God already determined in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, or we must all be left to our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in things that are not determined there, or there is a power inherent in the Church to determine such appendages of Worship as are not determined in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>To find every thing already determined in Scripture, needs very good eyes, and they that have made the most diligent search, are forced to confess they are not there: For though the Word of God be the undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted immovable Rule of Faith and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and therein he hath also prescribed how he will be worshipped, not only with the devotion of the inward, but the reverence of the outward man; and though under the Law, the very Form and Manner, as well as the Matter, of Publick Worship, was pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually expressed, yet under the Gospel it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49433:9"/> is not so; for the ministration of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit has given us an enlargement; and our great Law-giver having once for all secured the Substance, has left the Adjuncts and Circumstances of Christian Worship, to the pious and prudent judgement of those whom he has made the Overseers of his Church; in whose determinations we are peaceably to acquiesce, lest we discover a greater regard to our own private Fancies, than to the Duty we owe to our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, <hi>who are set over us in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And seeing we have that general Canon of the Apostle, that <hi>all things be done de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently and in order;</hi> as it cannot but seem reasonable, that we conclude our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours the fittest to judge of what is such; so being expresly enjoyned <hi>to submit to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Ordinance of man for the Lords sake,</hi> and <hi>to obey them that have the rule over us in the Lord,</hi> our Obedience to such Injunctions and Decrees, must needs be thought <hi>a reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, where God does not bind us, why should we bind our selves? Where
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49433:10"/> things are not determined by Scripture, are we not all left to our own liberty, and hath not Christ made us free? This is the usual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and Scruple of those that separate themselves upon this score. To which I answer briefly; 1. That Christ hath freed us indeed from the Yoke of legal Observan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and from all opinion of their obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or necessity; but then he hath withal enjoyned us submission to our lawful Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours and Pastours, and we must not use our liberty as a cloak for our craftiness and disobedience: And though all things are lawful now to Christians, as if the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Law had never been given; yet what is expedient for the furtherance of Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, is left to our Governours to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. 2. That in some things we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together free, yea in all, where God or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture do not restrain us, or where authority does not interpose for the sake of Unity and Peace; but that in every thing we should be left to our liberty, is so wild a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, as needs no other confutation than the sad experience of the disorders and distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances that have hapned, where Tolerations
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49433:10"/> have made men extravagant, and Liberty licentious: the effect of which has been as bad or worse, as the Apostle taxed the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> with, [1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 26.] <hi>While eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one has a Psalm, has a Doctrine, has a Tongue, has a Revelation, has an Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> A confusion so great, as gave just oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to the Unbelievers and Prophane, to say <hi>they were mad</hi> [v. 23.] and so worthy the Apostles severe reprehension, that it oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned that standing and unalterable Rule in the Church of God, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order; Let all things be done to edifying.</hi> To this I onely add, that there never was, nor at this day is, a consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Church upon Earth, but what hath exercised the same power for concluding their own Members: This the Fathers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Councils all along have practised, according to the pattern of the Apostles themselves in this first Council at <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> And such was the meek and submissive tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Christians in those days, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out disputing the Authority which made the Decrees, or quarrelling at the lawfulness of the things enjoyned, they freely acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>esced,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49433:11"/> and joyfully complied with 'em. Which leads me to the</p>
            <p n="2">[2] Proposition, <hi>That Decrees well made and promulgated ought to be kept.</hi> I say, well made, that we may not flatter Humanity so far, unless it be inspired from above, as to count it infallible; it is suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in all humane Constitutions, that our Superiours be morally assured of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness or expediency of what they enjoyn; and if their Decrees be delivered, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise published, being first advisedly made, either agreeable to the rules of Decency and Order, or conducing to the ends of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Peace, they ought to be as strictly observed as they were solemnly enacted; that is, They are</p>
            <p n="1">1. To be kept and preserved, and 2. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed and practised; for the word without any straining will bear very well both sences.</p>
            <p>(1.) They are to be kept &amp; preserv'd as use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Records, to which we may have recourse in case of doubt or difficulty: For, alas! we
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49433:11"/> are all but of yesterday, and know (as it were) nothing; little to be sure without the information of those that have gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, who have left the effects of their Piety and Wisdom behind, for the benefit and example of Posterity: And if there has been a Church, and men of great Holiness and Learning have flourished in it long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we were born, how shall we be able to know the mind of former Generations, or copy out their patterns of Virtue, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse with those of fore-going Ages, unless the Writings of Learned men, and much more the Decrees of venerable Councils be carefully preserved, that so we may first know, and then <hi>earnestly contend for the Faith which was once delivered to the Saints,</hi> then written by the will of God in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and has been propagated down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards unto us by these means. To the Book of God we look in the first place, which is <hi>able to make us wise unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> being <hi>thoroughly furnished</hi> thence <hi>to every good word and work;</hi> and if any doubt arise in the interpretation, we refer our selves to the first and purest Antiquity:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49433:12"/> To Christ alone, as the great Authour and finisher of our Faith, and the directour of our Lives; To the Apostles and Evangelists, as the first Preachers and Writers of his and their own acts; To the primitive Fathers and Councils, as the best Keepers and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters of the whole. This was the Rule most religiously observed by <hi>our holy Mother,</hi> in the happy reformation of her Doctrine, Discipline, and Government tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apostolical; in her Homilies and Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Constitutions and Decrees, Orthodox and Godly, Pure and Peaceable. And I take the boldness to add, that this is enough under the protection of God and the King, to preserve her still in unity and peace, and to secure her always from all the innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and corruptions of any usurping or dividing Sect. And blessed be God that we have such Helps and Writings of the Ancients in so great a measure safe and uncorrupt, that all the Monuments of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity are not fallen into the hands of <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> nor yet inclosed within the Walls of the envious <hi>Vatican;</hi> That Providence has in all Ages raised up such
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49433:12"/> persons as have been instrumental to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the Records of the Church as well as the Scriptures, not only from Moths and Worms, but from the more malicious cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of an <hi>Expurgatory Index.</hi> But is there then no better use to be made of Decrees, than Antiquaries make of dusty Monuments, who keep 'em only to look on, or to shew to others? Yes without doubt, much better. For,</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are made and preserved that they may be practised; for this indeed is the true keeping of 'em, and the design of making 'em: and if every thing is to be esteemed according to the value of its end, then these of all things were made to little purpose, if not to be obey'd and practised. For as bonds are not made to shew that men can write, but to carry an obligation with 'em, so are Decrees and Canons ordained, not onely to be committed to writing, but as Laws to be put in execution; not made barely as evidences of the Superiours power, but as the Rule of our obedience. When a Law is made, it is always intended as a Rule of their actions to whom it is given, and hence
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49433:13"/> obedience is at once the end and the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction also of a Law; for when it takes ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect by being duly observed, then and not till then it receives its final accomplishment; it is what it ought to be, when the subject <hi>executes</hi> what the giver of the Law <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> I speak not only of smaller injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though these also, where the matter is good, or at least indifferent, and the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity sufficient, oblige the inferiour to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; but of those chiefly which after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation had, are passed into <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Acts,</hi> and have received their force and obligation from the Supreme and Imperial Power; to which the people themselves have virtually given their consent before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, and are always supposed by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the thing, to be afterwards concluded by 'em: And when such as these are once enacted and fixed for the good of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, for men to stick, or draw back, to boggle and dispute, or else to pick and choose which they will obey and which not, what is it else, but to set up themselves as Judges of the Law, to make their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, or humour, or pride the Standard of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49433:13"/> the Publick, and even to be false to their own Acts? what is it else but tacitly at least to reproach their Soveraign, as though he had done what he ought not, to make his Authority vile and contemptible among the people, to set an ill example to their fellow-Subjects, who may equally claim the like exemption, to contradict the reason and end of all Constitutions, and overthrow the foundations of all Government both in Church and State?</p>
            <p>But is there no allowance then to be made for private Consciences, for men that are <hi>tender,</hi> or <hi>weak,</hi> or <hi>doubtful,</hi> or <hi>erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous?</hi> I put 'em together, because though they differ in the notion, yet they usually a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in their disobedience, and a brief an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer will serve 'em all, whether the allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be real, or onely in pretence. If Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science be only pretended, I need not tell, what horrid things have been done in the Land under this disguise, nor yet how easie it is for every crafty or designing person to put on the same cloak: it is well known how oft it has been made the great <hi>Palladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> of Sedition and Schism, of Rapine and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49433:14"/> Sacriledge, of Treason and Murder, and what not? and if we wanted instances of a later date, which yet are fresh and reeking, there is a day at hand, I mean the <hi>Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of this Month,</hi> wherein they are all exemplified with horrour. But admit the mans Conscience be really <hi>tender,</hi> that is, to speak properly, timorous of offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God the great Law - giver; How comes his duty to Governours to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in the case? is not this a part of the Divine Law? and can there be a greater offence against this part, as plain and sacred as the rest, than what is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted against the Parent of our Country, and Gods Vicegerent upon earth? whose Authority by his own appointment is second to his own, and must not by any means be left out in the account. Put the case again, his Conscience be <hi>weak,</hi> that is, ignorant or uninstructed in his duty; what better secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity can such an one have, than the Laws to direct him, and the wisdom of his Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to instruct him? if he be so weak, that he knows not what to do for himself, who fitter to be his Guardian than he that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tects and takes care of him, who more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49433:14"/> or able to teach him, than his lawful guides, <hi>whose lips preserve knowledge?</hi> But what if he be <hi>doubtful</hi> and unresolved, least he may probably sin, in this or that instance of obedience? How comes he to doubt of one side onely? to find faults and flaws in the Laws, and none in his own breast? Let him lay the obligations he has to obedience in one scale, and all his doubts and scruples in the other, and if Authority cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the ballance, 'tis a sign he makes a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry light thing of it: But whether it move him or no, this is certain, that a bare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability on one hand, can never discharge him from obeying an express precept on the other: The rule of his duty is fixed, his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is confessed to be in suspense; let the certain duty determine the uncertain and nice opinion. And as for the case of <hi>erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous</hi> Consciences, it scarce deserves to be considered, because Arguments or Counsel here can get no admittance; for though they be all mistaken, and sometimes as opposite to each other, as they are contrary to truth, yet none are willing to confess themselves in the wrong: were that but once acknowledged as it ought, the way would be opened for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49433:15"/> better information, and the power of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son would soon prevail. But still I confess this is the most perplexing case that a man can possibly bring himself into, since he must needs run himself into sin, whether he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows his Conscience, or goes against it: if he suffers it to lead him while he continues in his errour, having means sufficient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie his judgment, though his perswasion be never so strong, the man is nevertheless a sinner; for otherwise St. <hi>Paul</hi> before his Conversion, while <hi>he verily thought with himself, that he ought to do many things contrary to the Nome of Jesus,</hi> must be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted innocent; though afterwards (we know) he confessed himself upon that score to be <hi>the chief of sinners:</hi> If he goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it, though he be in an errour, he is deemed notwithstanding to sin against his Conscience, because he resists the best light he has at present, &amp; would in all probability do the same, should he happen to have better.</p>
            <p>An hard case indeed, for which he may thank his false Teachers or himself, or both together: And this one would think were enough to make a man jealous over the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49433:15"/> of his Conscience with a godly jealousie when ever it tempts him to gainsay the Established Laws; to root out of his mind prejudice and passion, and by respects, and to open his ear to the charitable instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his Superiours; to make him sit down and calmly consider what a sad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition he is in, and by what evil principles he came to be seduced into it; for here he may assuredly conclude, this is none of the ways of God, but some corruption of his own heart or life; for God cannot be the Author of sin, much less necessitate his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to run into it. But since there is no end of asking Questions, and raising Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, it is time we hasten to consider,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The benefit that accrues to the Church, by the due making and keeping of Decrees,</hi> which is the Third Proposition from the Text, and is here expressed in a double instance.</p>
            <p n="1">[1.] In the confirmation of such as are already Believers. And</p>
            <p n="2">[2.] In gaining new Converts to the Faith, <hi>And so were the Churches,</hi> &amp;c. Of which I shall speak as briefly as may be, that I may leave a little room for as short an Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49433:16"/>
            <p>The mind of man in Religion, before it is well instructed and grounded, is a very uncertain thing, doubtful which way to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, and what it should most adhere to; and as in matters of Faith, there are divers and strange winds of Doctrine, whereby they that are unlearned and unstable are toss'd to and fro; so in matters of practice, there are numberless Rites and usages, which as all cannot be observed, so neither can all be omitted; and therefore to determine what are needful and becoming, no better satisfaction to a sincere Christian, than there to acquiesce where his Superiours have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terposed their Wisdom and Authority, as fittest to judge, and most likely to know what may lawfully be done in such cases, and what is at once most agreeable both to the <hi>purity</hi> and <hi>peaceableness</hi> of our holy Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>And while the scrupulous Dissenter trifles away his zeal, and mispends his spirits in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending about the Rites and Circumstantials of Religion, the humble and peaceable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, that with a meek submission performs what he finds enjoyned, which he is sure can
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49433:16"/> never be sinful, being no way repugnant to the Law of God, feels more of the life and power of inward Christianity, and disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers more of that blessed temper of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Saints, who were so far from disobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or repining at the Decrees of their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, that <hi>they rejoyced at the consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on [c.</hi> 15. 31.] they were glad at their hearts to have their differences thus compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, that so they might live in peace, and serve God together as one man. That was one happy effect of their Superious decisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>the Churches</hi> thereby <hi>were established in the Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[2.] In gaining new Converts, and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men over to the true Religion; <hi>they increased in number daily.</hi> As no greater scandal to Religion than Dissentions and Differences among them that pretend to it, especially when men boggle at things which the Church declares to be <hi>indifferent in themselves,</hi> and <hi>necessary only as to use</hi> for peace and comliness-sake; so no greater im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment to the gaining of Proselites, since that profession may justly be suspected by strangers, where they that should adorn it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49433:17"/> by the meekness and submission of their tempers, are either quarrelling with their fellows, or murmuring at their Governours: But where unity and agreement appear in the life, it brings credit and votaries to the Doctrine, and makes men honour the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession; and then does Religion appear in the beauty of holiness, when righteousness and peace, obedience &amp; charity do kiss each other. So much does order and unity promote our common profession, so much <hi>does the making and keeping Decrees</hi> for that end, <hi>conduce to the establishment and increase of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shut up all with two or three inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and so commend you to the grace of God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>If Decrees may be made for the well governing and ordering of the Church of Christ,</hi> how unreasonable then are they who separate themselves from the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Established Church, because she makes such Decrees for the regulating and edifying her own Members; nay who alleadge this as the chief, if not the onely reason why they forsake her, because she
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49433:17"/> makes such Decrees to be kept? If they might be left to their own choice, perhaps they would observe the things which she enjoyns; but the very enjoyning 'em (it seems) is that which troubles 'em, and which makes 'em cry out of burdens laid upon their Consciences which they are not able to bear. To these I have many things to say, which I shall briefly comprize in this short disjunction. If our Governours have not power to choose and enjoyn such indifferent things as they judge most conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for Order and Unity, then they have no power at all to enjoyn any thing: for what is commanded of God in his Word, they cannot forbid; what is forbidden there, they cannot command; their power ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not to these things, nor can the worst of their enemies say they ever claim'd it: Wherefore one of these two must needs follow, either that their power extends to those things which are neither commanded nor forbidden, or that it extends to none at all: If any man be so hardy as to say, that his Governours have no power at all, the Magistrate is fitter to decide that point
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49433:18"/> than the Minister; if he allows 'em to have any, then he must needs confess 'tis in those things which are of an indifferent na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture according to the rules of decent Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and godly Discipline, such as are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally laid down in the Scripture, and suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for any sober and peaceable Christi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an to warrant his practice of 'em.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If <hi>Decrees well made ought to be kept,</hi> then let those who allow the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be exhorted seriously to consider what obligation they are under to shew their conformity to such Decrees, for the sake of their own and the Churches peace, and for the benefit of others, that so they may be induced to follow their good example. We have seen by a long and lamentable experience how much Religion has suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered since the Discipline and Decrees of the Church lost their esteem, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the open quarrels of those that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject 'em, but also by the coldness or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence, or indifferency of some that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to approve 'em. I cannot stay to name all the particulars, but shall onely
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49433:18"/> instance in those orders which concern our publick Prayers: If we carelesly absent our selves from 'em, or when we are present behave our selves irreverently as though we were no ways concern'd in 'em, what do we else but put a new Objection into the mouths of deserters, and alienate their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions so much the more from our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion? For this is a natural consequence, and it turns with some force upon us, if these people that pretend so much to love the Orders and Prayers of the Church make so light of 'em, we cannot but judge, that while they neglect 'em themselves or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functorily perform 'em, they confirm us in our Opinion, that there is no great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to be obtained by 'em: Wherefore that we lend 'em no such Objection nor scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize the Church whereof we are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, let us constantly frequent 'em, and Religiously joyn our Devotion in 'em, with the hearty affection of the inward, and the reverent behaviour of the outward man; and in both let us keep the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rees and Rules which the Church hath ordained, that God in all things may be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49433:19"/> glorified in ours <hi>as in all the Churchees of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If <hi>the keeping Decrees conduce</hi> so much <hi>to the good</hi> and welfare <hi>of the Church,</hi> then hence we learn once for all, which is the best expedient either for cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring divisions, or for restoring and establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing Peace among us; even the same which the Apostles themselves put it practice, of the same age and prescription with Christianity it self. And while divers men for some little ends are pleasing themselves with divers schemes and models of their own devising, which are too well known to be here recited, we have reason to bless God who hath put it into the heart of our Governours to shew 'em all <hi>a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way,</hi> not to let down the Laws to the humours of the people, which at first hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring sounds absurdly, but to bring up the people, to the measure of the Laws, which needs no proving, and speaks for it self.</p>
            <p>And as we doubt not but God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with the enforcement of those Laws in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49433:19"/> particular, which provide for the solemnity and decency of his own worship; as we are well assured that God hears the Prayers which are daily made before him with the uniform devotion of all the good Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans throughout the Realm, since he hath so often answer'd 'em with a most remarkable blessing, in giving deliverance to <hi>his Church,</hi> protection and strength and safety to <hi>his Anointed;</hi> so we are hence encouraged to hope that they will find but few, who shall presume to oppose 'em any longer, when the Supreme Pleasure upon Earth is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise generally known, and that it shall be so and so done to the Cause and to the Church, to the Persons and the Interest, which the King himself is resolved to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and thus delighteth to Honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the God of Patience and Consolation grant you to be like minded one towards another according to Christ Jesus: That ye may with one mind and one mouth glorifie God even the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ. And I beseech you (Brethren</hi>) by the same prevailing Name, <hi>that ye all speak the same thing, and that there be no divisions among you; but that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49433:20"/> ye be perfectly joyned together in the same mind, and in the same judgment.</hi> 'Tis the Prayer and the Exhortation of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the one for the <hi>Romans,</hi> the other to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians;</hi> and I cannot conclude better than in Praying again as our Church hath prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, <hi>That we may shew forth our thankfulness unto God for his wonderful Conversion, by following the</hi> Counsel and <hi>holy Doctrine which he taught, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49433:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>